<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Geological Survey, New England Water Science Center</origin><pubdate>20191015</pubdate><title>Crosswalk Table Between NHDPlus V2.1 and its Accompanying Watershed Boundary Dataset Snapshot of 12-Digit Hydrologic Units</title><geoform>tabular digital data</geoform><onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9CFXHGT</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>A crosswalk table between NHDPlus version 2.1 flowlines (using the unique field COMID) and the Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD) 12-digit-hydrologic units (HU-12) is provided for the 48 contiguous United States. The crosswalk table provides a WBD HU-12 assignment for every networked flowline in the NHDPlus. In this way, the network developed for navigation and modeling, NHDPlus, is aligned with accounting units of the WBD HU-12s to the extent possible given the assumptions that were made in creating each.

A crosswalk table for NHDPlus isolated sinks was produced by a simple overlay process where the sinks were assigned HU-12 values based on their position relative to the WBD snapshot HU-12s. This table was integrated with the flowline associations into one crosswalk table for both feature types.

There is good alignment between aggregated NHDPlus catchments and WBD HU-12 units in many locations. These are areas where the flows and chemical or nutrient loads that are accumulated leave the HU-12 at a single outlet and are passed down to the next HU-12 downstream (or to the coast) as is assumed in the WBD model.

A second pass through the data was made to account for any secondary outlet from each HU-12. The location of a secondary outlet with a significant drainage from that HU was identified in the alignment with NHDPlus. This resulted in a reduction in areas of mismatch as well as an improved crosswalk table. 

The crosswalk table should be used with caution in areas where efforts could be made to improve the data.  For example, with medium-resolution NHD, a better definition of flow direction of the flowlines in Southern Florida would result in more flowlines being included in the “networked” flowlines with catchments, and that, in turn, would result in better alignment between NHDPlus catchments and HU-12s. Correcting errors in either the medium-resolution NHD or WBD would improve the alignment between the two datasets.</abstract><purpose>Both datasets, NHDPlus and Watershed Boundary Dataset can be used as building blocks for stream‐water‐quality modeling analysis and reporting.  Each has its strengths and weaknesses.  Care and an understanding of these networks should be considered when employing appropriate applications.</purpose></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2019</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>ground condition</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-125.4199</westbc><eastbc>-66.1816</eastbc><northbc>49.4967</northbc><southbc>24.1267</southbc></bounding><descgeog>Contiguous USA</descgeog></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>inlandWaters</themekey></theme><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>NHDPlus</themekey><themekey>Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD)</themekey><themekey>12-digit Hydrologic Unit (HUC12)</themekey><themekey>flowlines</themekey><themekey>sinks</themekey><themekey>COMID</themekey></theme><theme><themekt>USGS Metadata Identifier</themekt><themekey>USGS:5c86a747e4b09388244b3da1</themekey></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>Contiguous USA</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None.  Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst><useconst>None.  Users are advised to read the data set's metadata thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, New England Water Science Center</cntorg><cntper>Richard Moore</cntper></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>331 Commerce Way</address><city>Pembroke</city><state>NH</state><postal>03275</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>603-226-7800</cntvoice><cntemail>rmoore@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>The flowlines were checked multiple times for mismatches in the HUC-12 number and improved on each pass through the data set. The accuracy of the HUC-12 assignments depends on the congruence of the 2 source data sets (NHDPlus v2 and WBD), which do not perfectly align. See Abstract and Process Steps for more information.</attraccr></attracc><logic>There are 2,698,739 unique feature ids with no duplication. 588 records have no HUC_12 value due to being just beyond the border of the United States where this version of the WBD data does not extend as far as the NHDPlus data, and these were assigned -9999.</logic><complete>The flowlines and sinks included here are within the contiguous United States (Vector Processing Units (HydroRegions) 01 through 18 from NHDPlus version 2 data). Every networked flowline and every sink that is not coded as a "BurnLineEvent network end" is included.</complete><lineage><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Lucinda McKay, Horizon Systems Corporation</origin><origin>Timothy Bondelid, Independent Consultant</origin><origin>Tommy Dewald, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</origin><origin>Craig M. Johnston, U.S. Geological Survey</origin><origin>Richard B. Moore, U.S. Geological Survey</origin><origin>Alan Rea, U.S. Geological Survey</origin><pubdate>20160510</pubdate><title>National Hydrography Dataset (NHD) Plus Version 2.1, 1:100,000-scale</title><geoform>vector digital data</geoform><onlink>http://horizon-systems.com/NHDPlus/NHDPlusV2_data.php</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>100000</srcscale><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>2012</begdate><enddate>20160510</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>NHDPlusv2.1</srccitea><srccontr>Flowline and sink features</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)</origin><origin>U.S. Department of Agriculture - Natural Resource Conservation Service (NRCS)</origin><origin>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)</origin><pubdate>20160510</pubdate><title>Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD) 12-Digit Hydrologic Unit Codes</title><geoform>vector digital data</geoform><onlink>https://www.usgs.gov/core-science-systems/ngp/national-hydrography/watershed-boundary-dataset</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>1980</begdate><enddate>20160510</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>WBD</srccitea><srccontr>HUC_12 values associated with NHDPlus features</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Curtis Price, U.S. Geological Survey</origin><pubdate>20160606</pubdate><title>WBD HU12 Pour Points derived from NHDPlus</title><geoform>vector digital data</geoform><onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/5762b664e4b07657d19a71ea</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20160606</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>FPP</srccitea><srccontr>Publication includes from pour points (fpp), to pour points (tpp), and vector pour points (vpp). The FPP set was used here as input to processing step 2 to match NHDplus flowlines to pourpoints of HU-12s.</srccontr></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Identified points that best define the outlets of each WBD HU-12 based on the location where the greatest raster flow accumulation from within the HU-12 leaves that HU-12 (Curtis Price, 20160606, WBD HU12 Pour Points published at NHDPlus: ScienceBase https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/5762b664e4b07657d19a71ea).  The version of the HU-12s and flow rasters used for this process were those that come with NHDPlusV2.1.  Data output from this step (entitled “From pour points (fpp)”) was used as input to the next step.</procdesc><srcused>NHDPlusv2.1</srcused><srcused>WBD</srcused><procdate>20160606</procdate><srcprod>FPP</srcprod></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Identified the NHDPlus flowline(s) that best match the pour points from step 1 to further define the outlets of the HU-12s.  This was accomplished by use of the script, HUC12_NHDPlusAssociation.py written by Craig Johnston, included with this Data Release.  The version of this script presented has been modified slightly to read fields in NHDPlusHR format.  Pour points removed from the input dataset prior to running the program were those associated with HU-12s draining directly to the coast, empty HU-12s (without NHD features), and closed HU-12s.  After running the program, results were manually reviewed and, in some cases, modified to better define the outlet flowlines. [May 2016 to February 2018].</procdesc><srcused>FPP</srcused><procdate>20180212</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Aggregated NHDPlus catchments into WBD HU-12-equivalent units by navigating the NHDPlus network between outlet flowlines identified in step 2 and assigning the intervening flowlines and their catchments to the HU-12 of the downstream outlet flowline.  This was accomplished by use of the script, AccumulateUPAssignHUC12IDs.py also written by Craig Johnston in 2017.  The script also accompanies this Data Release.  After running the script, the flowlines and catchments associated with HU-12s draining directly into the coast, or closed HU-12s were assigned HU-12 IDs by using a simple overlay process using ArcMap.</procdesc><procdate>20180212</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Compared NHDPlus-based HU-12s and WBD HU-12 units across the Nation and identified areas of difference.  The areas of disagreement occurred largely in Southern Florida, throughout the more arid portions of Western US, and the areas of complex drainage within the area of the Mississippi delta (see figure 1).</procdesc><procdate>201802</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Ran steps 1, 2, and 3 over again, but, for steps 1 and 2, having it operate just on the areas of mismatch (blue areas in the map).   In this way, secondary outlets and associated upstream flowlines and catchments were identified for many of the HU-12s.  Much of the area of mismatch still remained, so an overlay process was undertaken using ArcMap.  In this process, flowlines associated with areas of mismatch greater than 1 square kilometer were assigned to the HU-12 over which the midpoint of each flowline fell.</procdesc><procdate>201805</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Results were compiled as a table or Crosswalk between NHDPlus V2.1 catchments/flowlines and the NHDPlusV2.1 WBD HU-12 Snapshot.  This crosswalk table between NHDPlus flowline and WBD HU-12 is provided as this data release.  The crosswalk table provides a WBD HU-12 assignment for every networked flowline in the NHDPlus within the contiguous United States. To this table, isolated sinks and their HU-12 (assigned by simple overlay) were added.  Thus, the network developed for navigation and modeling, NHDPlus, was aligned with accounting units of the WBD HU12s to the extent possible given the assumptions that were made in creating each dataset.</procdesc><procdate>20190530</procdate></procstep></lineage></dataqual><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>CrosswalkTable_NHDplus_HU12</enttypl><enttypd>A comma-delimited table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd><enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>SOURCEFC</attrlabl><attrdef>Source Feature Class (“NHDFlowline” or “Sink”)</attrdef><attrdefs>NHDPlus v2 User Guide; ftp://ftp.horizon-systems.com/NHDplus/NHDPlusV21/Documentation/NHDPlusV2_User_Guide.pdf</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>NHDFlowline</edomv><edomvd>The featureID represents a flowline</edomvd><edomvds>NHDPlus</edomvds></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Sink</edomv><edomvd>The featureID represents a sink point</edomvd><edomvds>NHDPlus</edomvds></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>FEATUREID</attrlabl><attrdef>Unique numeric identification of the NHDPlus v2 feature. For a flowline, this is the COMID (positive numbers). For a sink, this is the SinkID (negative numbers).</attrdef><attrdefs>https://www.epa.gov/waterdata/nhdplus-national-hydrography-dataset-plus</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Unique feature identifiers between -504212 and -6006 for Sink features and between 101 and 948100740 for flowline features.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>HUC_12</attrlabl><attrdef>12-Digit hydrologic unit code associated with the NHDPlus v2 feature</attrdef><attrdefs>WBD</attrdefs><attrdomv><codesetd><codesetn>Federal Standards and Procedures for the National Watershed Boundary Dataset (WBD)</codesetn><codesets>Section 6: Geospatial Data Structure and Attributes (https://pubs.usgs.gov/tm/11/a3/)</codesets></codesetd></attrdomv></attr></detailed></eainfo><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg><cntper>GS ScienceBase</cntper></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address><city>Denver</city><state>CO</state><postal>80225</postal><country>United States</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice><cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Digital Data</formname></digtinfo><digtopt><onlinopt><computer><networka><networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9CFXHGT</networkr></networka></computer></onlinopt></digtopt></digform><fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees></stdorder></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20220824</metd><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Laura Hayes </cntper><cntper>Richard Moore</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Northeast Region</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Physical Scientist / Hydrologist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>331 Commerce Way</address><city>Pembroke</city><state>NH</state><postal>03275</postal><country>United States</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>603-226-7800</cntvoice><cntfax>603-226-7894</cntfax><cntemail>lhayes@usgs.gov </cntemail><cntemail>rmoore@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv></metainfo></metadata>